Guide to the Gabriel Paris Collection Relating to France, May 1968
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gabriel Paris collection relating to France, May 1968
1968-1978
GEN MSS 949
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.63
(3 boxes) + 24 broadside folders
Paris, Gabriel, 1924-
Gabriel Paris (1924-2000)
Gabriel Paris was an artist, painter, and activist. He was born in Uzès, France, but spent most of his life in Paris, where he died in 2000.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Sketchbooks, 1968-1974. II. Photographs, 1968. III. Political tracts, pamphlets, and newspaper clippings, 1968-1978. IV. Posters, lithographs, and maquettes, 1968-1970.
Scope and Contents
The Gabriel Paris collection consists of materials related to the May 1968 protests in Paris, France. The collection contains three screen print posters produced at the Atelier populaire (ex-École des Beaux-Arts) in May-June 1968, several signed lithographs produced between May-July 1968, eleven original maquettes (1968-1970), and two sketchbooks created by Gabriel Paris, each of which contains numerous drawings and sketches that were used in the production of protest posters. The collection also contains 45 black and white photographic prints taken by Paris, which document the May 1968 protests, and over 200 printed political tracts, which were collected by Paris from 1968-1978.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Glenn Horowitz Bookseller, Inc., 2012.
Artists -- France; General Strike, France, 1968; Labor movement -- France -- Paris; Protest movements -- France -- Paris; Political activists -- France; Political posters, French -- France -- Paris; France -- Politics and government -- 1958-1969 -- Posters; Protest posters -- France -- Paris -- 20th Century; Lithographs -- France -- 20th Century; Photographic prints -- France -- 20th Century; Printed ephemera -- France -- 20th Century; Sketchbooks -- France -- 20th Century; Artists -- France -- 20th Century; Painters -- France -- 20th Century; Paris, Gabriel, 1924-
- Sketchbooks, 1968-1974; Series I; 28 x 38 cm; (2 sketchbooks)
  Scope and Contents
  Each sketchbook contains a variety of poster art sketches and designs, many of which are cut out and affixed directly to the pages.
  - Chronique a fleur de peau Mai 68–June 69, (60 pages) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Title is printed on the bottom of the cover, in black ink. Also printed on the cover, in pencil: "Gabriel Paris: Chronique a fleur de peau 1968–74 / Notes et croquis."
    Note from the dealer: Chronique a fleur de peau was the proposed title for an autobiographical film that Paris had been working on since the mid-seventies until the time of his death in 2000.
  - Projects dessins politiques et affiches, (60 pages) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Title printed on bottom of cover, in black ink. The sketchbook also contains a few newspaper clippings, including an editorial piece by Robert Merle from Le Monde, dated 1974 May 25.
- Photographs, 1968 May; Series II; 45 photographic prints, black and white, 7.5 x 8 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
  The photographs are affixed to four separate cardboard pages.
- Political tracts, pamphlets, and newspaper clippings, 1968-1978, undated; Series III; approximately 200 items
  Arrangement
  Arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Political tracts and pamphlets, 1968-1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
    Contains a variety of items collected by Gabriel Paris from 1968-1978. Over twenty of the items were published by a community of artists, "MontmARTre aux artistes," of which Gabriel Paris was a member. A few pamphlets detail the 1970s arrest of 3 labor activists -- Houdet, Rousseau, and Ordennez-Aurioles -- who were arrested for putting up posters demanding the release of Devaux, Herve, Trouilleux and Divet. The collection also includes publications attributed to the Jeunesse Communiste Revolutionnaire (JCR), Parti Socialiste Unifie (PSU), Parti Communiste Francais (PCF), L'Union Naitional des Etudiants de France (UNEF), and more.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1977, undated; (4 items) (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 1)
    Includes three clippings and a copy of l'Humanité (two-page special edition), dated Monday, 1977 September 26.
- Posters, lithographs, and maquettes, 1968-1970; Series IV; (29 items)
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Adieu De Gaulle, 1968 May; 74 x 105 cm; Lithograph. On cardstock. Red and black ink. (Box 27 (Broadside))
    Signed "47/50 Gabriel Paris" in pencil. Includes a long quote attributed to "Combat no. 7423, Michel Ragon ," as well as the following text: '20 " 07 Gare de Lyon - Vendredi, 24 Mai 1968.'
  - Alerte à la drogue, 1969 September-October; 57 x 78 cm; Original maquette. Black ink. Poster board. (Box 13 (Broadside))
    Signed "Gabriel Paris." Stamped "Chronique a fleur de peau. Gabriel Paris."
  - Comite Viet-Nam, 60 x 80 cm; Original maquette. Black ink and masking tape. (Box 5 (Broadside))
    Signed "GP"
  - Les CRS VEAUtent VOUi à De Gaulle, 50 x 65 cm; Screen print poster. Black ink. Newsprint. (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 2)
    Stamped "Atelier C8-H40."
  - Le Dernier Barrage, 1969; 50 x 65 cm; Original maquette. (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 3)
    Stamped "27 Avril 1969." Also includes repetitions of the word "NON" at the top of the poster.
  - De Gaulle n'est plus seul, 1968 May-June; 74 x 104 cm; Lithograph. Blue, red, and black ink. (Box 17 (Broadside))
    Signed "32/40 Gabriel Paris" in pencil.
  - De Gaulle n'est plus seul (recto); Untitled collage (verso), 1968 May-June; 67 x 103 cm (Box 10 (Broadside))
  - Deserteurs Americains Contre L'Amerique Imperialiste, 56 x 80 cm; Original maquette. Black ink. (Box 8 (Broadside))
    Depicts Richard Nixon's head, in cartoonish style, with Viet-Nam written on his forehead; on both sides of his head, there are a number of other geopolitical references, including Formosa, Greece, and Spain.
  - Il ne reste plus qu'à peindre des fleurs, 1968 July; 74 x 105 cm; Lithograph. Black, yellow, red, blue, and green ink. (Box 16 (Broadside))
    Signed "45/50 Gabriel Paris" in pencil.
  - L'Intox (recto) and Bleeding Skull (verso), 50 x 65 cm; Original maquette. Black and white ink (recto); Black, yellow, and red ink (verso). (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 4)
    Recto: includes a drawing of a parrot, which is being broadcast on television, delivering the following line: "Le Gaullisme rien que le Gaullisme et toujours le Gaullisme." Verso: stamped "Gabriel Paris, Mai / Juin 1968".
  - Je regarde l'avenir eclater dans les yeux, 1968 June 1; 78 x 116 cm; Original maquette. Black, red, and white ink. (Box 26 (Broadside))
    Dated "1.6.68." Dimensions written in pencil, top left. Also has the following: "Poems de Mai 7.6.1968"
  - Je regarde l'avenir eclater dans les yeux, 1968 May; 75 x 103 cm; Black and gray ink. (Box 24 (Broadside))
    Includes other phrases, such as "Le Chienlit c'est lui," and "Le Pouvoir est dans la rue."
  - Je regarde l'avenir eclater dans les yeux, 1968 May; 57 x 79 cm; Black and gray ink. (Box 9 (Broadside))
    Stamped "Gabriel Paris Mai 1968 / Ex-ecole des beaux arts."
  - Leur Campagne Commence / Notre Lutte Continue, 76 x 100 cm; Screen print poster. Green ink. (Box 11 (Broadside))
    Stamped "Atelier Populaire Ex-Ecole Des Beaux-Arts."
  - Oui/Non, 50 x 65 cm; Screen print poster, red ink. (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 5)
  - Toi mon camarade toi que j'ignorais, viens parle-nous / Contestation, 114 x 155 cm; Original maquette. Black, red, and gray ink. On heavy cardboard. Folded in half. (Box 19 (Broadside))
    Signed "Gabriel Paris Mai 1968."
  - Toi mon camarade toi que j'ignorais, viens parle-nous / Contestation, 1968 May; 58 x 78 ¾ cm; Black and white reproduction poster on cardstock. (Box 12 (Broadside))
    Signed "Gabriel Paris Mai 1968". Dimensions written in pencil.
  - Toi mon camarade toi que j'ignorais, viens parle-nous, 77 x 115 cm; Original maquette. Red and black ink. (Box 23 (Broadside))
  - Unite, 1968 May-June; 74 x 104 cm; Black and red ink. (Box 15 (Broadside))
    Signed "38/45 Gabriel Paris". Includes the phrase, "Dix ans c'est asser / dix ans c'est trop," as well as others.
  - Untitled [bleeding head, boot], Black and red ink.; 76 x 116 cm (Box 22 (Broadside))
  - Untitled [cop / flic, bleeding head, boot], 1968 May; Black and gray ink.; 74 x 103 cm (Box 18 (Broadside))
  - Untitled [cop / flic, bleeding head, boot], Red, black and gray ink. Folded in half.; 114 x 155 cm (Box 21 (Broadside))
  - Untitled [cop / flic, blood, boot], 1968 May; 58 x 80 cm; Black and gray ink. (Box 6 (Broadside))
  - Untitled [cop / flic, bleeding skull], 1968 May-June; 79 x 109 cm; On canvas. Black, yellow, red, and gray ink. (Box 20 (Broadside))
  - Untitled [cop / flic, bleeding skull], 1968 May-June; 75 x 116 cm; On cardboard. Black, yellow, red and gray ink. (Box 25 (Broadside))
    Signed "31/40 Gabriel Paris" in pencil.
  - Untitled [newspaper collage], 56 x 76 cm (Box 7 (Broadside))
    Collage of five newspaper clippings, primarily photographic. The only clipping with text has the following printed on it, "Paris Match No. 314 Du 2 Au 9 Avril 1955." On the top right of the poster, "compo 52 x 72" is written in pencil; "LAPIN" is written in the center.
  - Untitled [riot scene], 51 x 69 cm; Black, gray and red ink. Cardboard cutout. (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 6)
  - Untitled collage, 56 x 76 cm; Collage affixed to poster board. (Box 4 (Broadside))
    "compos 52 x 72" written in pencil, top right.
  - Untitled collage, 76 x 56 cm; Red and black ink, with newspaper print. (Box 14 (Broadside))
    "compo 52 x 72" written in pencil